[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-
radio.net se radio is brought to you by
the it computer society and by It
software Magazine online at computer.org
software are you a techsavvy developer
with an inquisitive mind SC radio has an
opening for a new volunteer host to join
the team and produce five episodes per
year contact show editor Robert bluman
at robert. bluman at gmail.com for
details welcome to software engineering
radio I'm your host Jeff dittle in this
episode I'll be discussing antifragile
architecture with Barry
O'Reilly Barry is CEO and founder of
black tulip technology he specializes in
designing antifragile software systems
he is a certified Information Technology
architect professional who has held
Chief Architect positions at Microsoft
and at idesign he has been a startup CTO
the worldwide lead for the solutions
architecture community at Microsoft and
founder of the Swedish Azure User Group
Barry is also a trainer for iasa the
International Association of software
Architects and a research student in the
area of complexity science and software
engineering
welcome to software engineering radio
Barry thanks Jeff so in a conversation
before this episode you said something
interesting you said all really good
Architects know something is wrong but
can't articulate it let's start our
conversation there what is wrong that
Architects notice but struggle to
articulate well I think U if if you look
at the experience of even really good
architects who who've had considerable
success across some sometimes very
lengthy careers um there's a discomfort
that exists because we all know that
being able to reproduce what we do or
being able to articulate or describe
what we do as Architects being able to
uh mentor and teach Junior Architects
how to react in different situations is
is incredibly difficult um and if you if
you discuss how um a particular
architect went about solving a
particular set of
problems um what you'll find is that
there's a lot of intuition
uh involved and intuition is something
that's very difficult to explain and
even more difficult to uh to teach and
we know that in in a lot of our projects
that there's always an element of luck
and that things are very very rarely in
our control even though if you go to a
conference and watch an architect talk
about what they've delivered in a
particular project you'll see them talk
about how we did this and then we did
that and then we seen this problem come
in and then we solved it but we all know
that that's not not how it works in
reality there's a lot more iteration
there's a lot more mistakes um and the
people who are able to consistently
deliver um don't have a consistent
framework for delivering so there's no
single method or approach that actually
helps you uh guides you to be able to
deliver architecture especially when the
domains that you're working in are are
complex and this uh this makes us very
uneasy as Architects and it's a very
difficult convers ation to have because
very few people are brave enough to
stand up and say I'm not exactly sure
what I'm doing all the time um and it's
it's not really part of the culture of
our industry to be able to say that
interesting so a question there you
mentioned even that there's an element
of of luck or that a lot of people when
they present about architecture very
often they're giving us the success and
they're giving us the things that they
identify that they did but it sounds
like you're saying there's other
elements or factors that might have led
to their success that either they're not
mentioning or perhaps even they're not
exactly aware of can you expand on that
a little bit yes absolutely so in in any
successful Endeavor in a complex
environment um there going to be
elements of luck um because by
definition a complex environment is
something that we don't understand can't
model and definitely can't
control so they are going to be there
are always some elements of luck in that
and but there's also the fact that there
is is no framework there is no method
there is no step-by-step process that we
can execute on in order to be able to
cope with and deliver in that kind kind
of environment um you need to develop a
certain set of skills um that you aren't
going to be able to predict before you
start a project how that's going to work
what what you're going to do how you're
going to
execute um and so that that's what makes
us as Architects a little bit uneasy
because we live in in a world that's
defined uh that defines competence
through our ability to plan and to
execute so there's a British researcher
called Ralph Stacy who's a researcher
within complexity and management and he
wrote um a fantastic book called
complexity and organizational reality
and Stacy talks about something called
the dominant discourse of management and
the dominant discourse of management
tells us that the world Works in this
particular way that very smart people
usually management get together they
look at a problem they analyze the
problem they decide on a solution they
execute they deliver the solution and if
the solution works then they're deemed
to be competent if the solution doesn't
work then they're deemed to be
incompetent um and in complex situations
that never actually happens H and so
what we do and if you go and and a tip
for reading on this area is is the
absolutely fantastic and groundbreaking
book by Nasim TB it's called Fooled by
Randomness what we do do is when we
succeed or when we fail we then make up
a story afterwards about what it was
that we we did how we decided to execute
and those stories are all always much
more linear than they were in reality
because no one ever wants to admit that
we didn't know what was going to happen
we weren't in control the entire time
and successful Architects learn how to
be successful when they're not in
control all the time they don't have to
predict every step in a project or every
product choice or every component choice
to predict everything perfectly
um and in fact it very very rarely
happens like that and if it does happen
like that then you're working with
something that's very very simple okay
so you mentioned Simplicity just now and
previously you mentioned complexity so
perhaps you can help expand a little bit
on what is it that makes architecture in
particular software architecture a
complex environment versus a simple
environment so soft software projects um
can be simple they can also be compx Lex
um there's a if you want to understand
the difference between these things
there's a fantastic framework called
Kevan um which is developed by a guy
called Dave Snowden that helps us to
navigate the kind of problems that we're
trying to solve and helps us Orient
ourselves and understand am I working
with a simple problem a complicated
problem or or a complex problem and um
simple problems are things that we all
understand if I say to you make coffee
um you understand what to do I don't
have to communicate a whole bunch of
detail and there's hopefully not a whole
whole bunch of things that can go wrong
while you're doing that um complicated
things or or things like cars and
airplanes that have a lot of moving
Parts um that have to be put together
and and often need expert analysis in
order to make them work complicated
thing or complex things are things that
are beyond our understanding things that
we cannot predict things that we cannot
control things where we things where we
do not have uh a scientific
understanding of the behavior of the
system things like the weather human
systems economic systems human behavior
things can't be modeled with equations
or or predict or predicted accurately so
would somebody possibly argue that
software is complicated rather than
complex based on the definitions that
you just gave or or what might
differentiate those things yeah so the
thing that differentiates software is
that it is most of the time software is
is is complicated and when we say
complicated it means something requires
expert analysis in order to be able to
get it to work the vast majority of the
software that we build is complicated
the difference with software and other
mechanical things that are also
complicated is that we take this
complicated piece of software and we
force it to live in complex environments
so I take my complicated message bus and
and apis and clients um and I put them
into a complex environment and that
complex environment is a is a social
system of people of users of businesses
of
markets um and those things are
constantly warping and
changing um as well as the the
technology around them which is
constantly working and changing and we
force these complicated systems to live
in complex environments interesting yeah
and we make two we make two mistakes as
Architects and Engineers the first
mistake is that we assume that
complexity exists in our software and
you'll see this when we took when if you
take ask any hardened programmer about
complexity they'll talk about Big O
notation and psychomatic complexity
because because we're too inward looking
we believe that complexity exists in
code that's not true most of the time
the other thing that we do is that we
shut out complex and we focus on the
complicated so we don't care about the
people we don't care about the markets
we don't care about the the complex
environment that we make our software
live in we only really care as far as
the as the the compiler and then it's
someone else's problem um in a complex
environment a complex environment is is
determined by the fact that all of the
agents all of the acting parties in a
complex environment are intensely
interconnected and so the connection
between your software components your
decomposition your
choices um and the market and the people
around that software are so deep that
you cannot do a good job as an engineer
if you if you ignore them or if you
leave those things over to someone else
so you're saying that it's the
environment that we put these software
systems into that is complex so while
the system itself May simply be
complicated the environment in which
we're either deploying it or building it
or managing and maintaining it is what
brings in the complexity most of the
most of the time yes so one of the ways
that um that that we as humans work with
the complex systems is that we constrain
them and we constrain complex system
until it's uh until it's simple enough
for us to cope with and manage uh and a
good example of this is driving so the
the driving of
cars um when cars first appeared there
weren't any rules there weren't any any
regulations um and if you had just
bought your car around the around the
beginning of the last century and you
were driving down the road and someone
was driving towards you there was no
protocol about what you should do and So
eventually we started to constrain the
system so we said what we're going to
drive on this side the road or this side
of the road and then we add more
constraints we put white lines on the
road then we add even more constraints
we come with rounder bites and
eventually traffic lights and things
like driving licenses until it all seems
fairly obvious how we drive and but to
if you took someone from 1910 in one of
the first motor car uh Motorcars and and
made them Drive In in for example in
Italy today um they wouldn't be they
would find it kind of chaotic they would
not believe that it's a simple system so
what we do is we constrain and if you
look at what's happening in our industry
uh what we're doing in in cloud cloud is
you know a computer or a processor is
actually a complex thing because
anything can happen and what we do is we
we use Hardware architecture and we use
software architecture to constrain the
possible things that can happen and this
is our um both at the hardware level and
the software level this is our white
lines and roundabouts and our compiler
rules and and and and things like that
um and our networking rules and
eventually when something becomes simple
it becomes a commodity and the growth of
clud is that commodity constrained the
computer so much that we can stuff
millions of them in a container um in a
warehouse somewhere and have people plug
into it so we've we've conquered the
complexity of computing through
constraint um now it doesn't mean that
those systems aren't complex because
complexity never really goes away if one
of those constraints or something
changes complexity is very quick to re
rear its head but we've pretty much got
this one down to a level where we don't
need to think that much about it and as
software engineers at Enterprises it's
not our job because people at Microsoft
and Google that deal with that kind of
constraint with that kind of
complexity um the complexity that we you
and I have to deal with every day is
that when we build a system based on
these Cloud platforms we deliver it into
these complex
environments where there's a completely
different and much more
difficult set of concerns that must be
addressed and and the thing that I
always do in order to get people to
understand this is ask a very simple
question of an architect or a developer
what will your system do how will your
system behave if a competitor drops
their price in the business in the world
of business in the World Trade um there
are an infinite number of things that
can happen it's an incredibly complex
environment and a competitor drop in
their price is actually something that
we expect it shouldn't really be a
surprise um and if if you ask a business
person a CEO or CFO what are we going to
do if competitor drops their price then
they'll generally have a good answer or
to that question if you ask a developer
you'll you you generally get a blank
look as as in that's not my problem
right now if a competitor drops their
price the business has to respond in
some way you have to drop the price
yourself which impacts your margins or
you have to get out of that market or
you have to change your offering so that
it moves perhaps from a product to a
more service oriented offering and or
perhaps you want to buy that competitor
um exit that market move to a different
adjacency there's a whole bunch of
choices that can be made and every
single one of those choices is going to
have a massive impact on the
architecture of the system that you've
put in place the vast majority of
systems that we build because we're
inward looking because we think that
complexity is inside the software we
focus so much on the software we don't
understand the impact that that kind of
thing can have on the
perceived and the actual quality of our
software so that's an interesting point
it's sounds like you're making a
connection there between the need for
software engineers and Architects to
have a better understanding of the
business environment that their software
lives in is that is that right yes and
that's that's an argument that
Architects and architecture
organizations like aasa the
International Association of software
Architects have been making for for 15
years and but it's all been abstract and
it's always involved telling senior
developers that you need to know about
business you need to know about the
business you need to know about how the
business Works um and otherwise your
career will stall um my Approach L is to
say you need to understand how your
business works you need to understand
how business Works in general otherwise
your systems will feel eventually okay
uh in these in these complex
domains and I believe that we're moving
um as an industry we're moving towards a
new era um and so back in the in the
1930s um business was was something
thing in my mind was done by by large
men with cigars around fireplaces sure
and uh in the basement they had the
finance Geeks and the finance Geeks were
doing sums and ledgers and things like
that and at some stage around the the
time of Britain Woods the finance people
were invited up to the Fireside they
never really left and U we seen that at
its Pinnacle in the 1980s and I believe
that we are on the cusp of being invited
to the Fireside because we've been in
the bunker for a very long time and
deservedly so you might say um and we
are about to be invited to the Fireside
where we don't become an organization
that delivers software into a business
but we become a vital functioning part
of a business building and delivering
and refining software and so our ability
to respond in step with uh with a
business as part of a business rather
than than something that delivers to the
business uh is is going going to
fundamentally change our relationship
with Stak holders which means that when
a competitor drops their price it's our
job to be on that and make sure that we
react in time so we've talked a lot
about complexity so far and you
mentioned before Nim TB and the book
Fool by Randomness but this might be a
good place to segue into another one of
his books since our episode is titled
titled anti- fragile architecture so
maybe you can make the connection for
our listeners between complexity and the
con known as
antifragility complexity is something
that that as I said the vast majority of
people don't really understand and they
very little reason to understand it and
the key thing to understand is is that
there's a very big difference between
something that's complicated and
something that's complex um something
that's complex is is inherently
nonlinear in nature and it's
unpredictable uncontrollable and it's
beyond the reaches of our of our science
now we're programmed as people to seek
patterns to understand things to map
things out um and especially in the
business world as I mentioned DC
dominant discourse it it tends to make
us seek certainty and and that seeking
of certainty um gets us into an awful
lot of trouble especially as software
Engineers um complexity is a very
difficult subject and I think that um
Nasim Talib is on a fantastic job of
writing uh books that give you an
introduction complexity without all of
the heaviness that you might find in
other complexity literature H Fooled by
Randomness is a fantastic start it tells
us about our place in the universe and
the fact that we don't really understand
what's going on most of the time and
that we tend to in in invent little
stories about how things have happened
and and use things like hindsight bias
to convince ourselves that somehow we're
in
control um antifragile is a continuation
of that and in antifragile Talib
investigator it's the kind of systems
that when they're exposed to Randomness
when they're exposed to the stress
that's inherent in being exposed to
Randomness that these systems rather
than crumbling as as some systems would
do rather than simply weathering the
storm these systems actually use the the
stress of Randomness that they're
exposed to in order to become
stronger and the example the standard
example of this is when the the the
plague came to Europe in the 14th
century and when plague came to Europe H
A lot of people got sick and a lot of
people
died but now I 600 years later we're
still here we're significantly better
off than we were before there's a lot
more of us than there were before and
very few of us are going to die from
pneumonic or or ponic plague so our
immune systems and and as a collective
system European Society was able to
react to a form of stress that it had
never seen before
um which we call a a Black Swan
something that we couldn't have
predicted um we were and we've become
stronger and better for the exposure to
that stress even if we suffered for a
short while during that and the the
concept of antifragile then is any
system that's able to uh to not only
absorb but to use stress to make itself
stronger and if you look at any system
that we consider to be uh antifragile
which is resilient or Beyond resilience
as I would say you'll see that most of
those systems um the human immune system
economic systems political systems they
have become strong um they've become
resilient they've grown Beyond
resilience through the exposure to
stress not through design not through
some kind of Central Committee not
through some magical method um that
makes everything that makes everything
work or or some uh governing framework
but through the exposure to stress so
stressors and complexity it sounds like
there's a relationship there we spent a
lot of time earlier on talking about
complexity and now in the context of
antifragility you've mentioned stressors
so maybe you can explore uh that
connection a little bit so one of the
things that happens if you're a software
engineer and you read the book
antifragile um you cannot help yourself
from drawing parallels with our industry
and the inevitable question that you're
going to ask yourself is why don't we
build systems that get stronger longer
as they're exposed to stress exactly yes
and the truth is that we we're not
really we don't really have the right
way of thinking to do that because we
gather
requirements we build to those
requirements we test to those
requirements and we deliver things into
production which is the exact opposite
of uh of building to anti fragility and
there's a guy called Kenny Jones at
Nasa um who wrote an article um on on uh
on how we need to rethink How We Do
design because building to requirements
automatically makes a system fragile if
you build a system that's only Built to
satisfy its requirements which are very
often wrong confused and muddled and if
you build a system that will only
satisfy its requirements then that
system is naturally going to be fragile
to everything that you haven't built it
to be able to do and for example if you
build a system that uh has a spec that
says we need to have 500 calls per
second coming into this system um if
that system falls down at 501 calls then
you technically and contractually have
done your job but the perception of
quality in the minds of the people that
you've delivered that software to is
that you've delivered something with a
fairly low level of quality and and so
in in the in the minds of many of our
customers and and our partners that we
work with quality is is a measure of how
well a system responds to complexity not
how well a system responds to a spec
that was written several years ago and
nobody can remember who wrote it or why
and so what we need to do is to start
rethink thinking how do we design our
systems H and and the concept of stress
is very very important uh now there's a
guy called David parnas uh back in
1972 uh who who wrote an article on
decomposing a system into modules and he
talked about how we as software
Engineers tend to break a system down
into into functional components
something that he called conventional
decomposition and and that this was
quite damaging and limited the life
cycle of a system system in the next
step then he said that we should do
something called non non-conventional
decomposition where we break a system
down and according to what is going to
change and that's a fantastic idea and
definitely an evolution from from what
from what we've been doing previously
and it turns out that we pretty much
ignored what parna said and continued uh
breaking systems down according to
function um for many many years and and
we're still doing it today um but beyond
Paras then if we look at complex systems
if we look at the system outside the
piece of code that we're going to build
it's actually impossible for us to
determine what's going to change in a
complex system U now we might be able to
there are some obvious things that are
going to change so um you should you
shouldn't hardcode your database strings
um you shouldn't uh weld your system to
a particular operating
system these things are fairly obvious
and standard systems engineering should
take care of that um and so there are
things that will change and you design a
system for those things that are going
to change it's going to be a little bit
more robust than a system that's not
designed for those things that are going
to change but outside of that in a
complex environment there are millions
and millions and and trillions and an
uncountable number of things that can
possibly change and and when those
changes happen they will produce stress
on your system and rather than
identifying these all these individual
things that are going to change around
the system which is impossible in a
complex environment um we need to be
able to talk to this the ability of the
system to withstand stress and that
removes us one step from talking about
uh things that may change in an
environment because we're never going to
be able to do that we're never going to
be able to predict it we're never going
to be able to agree on what to focus our
energy on so instead we focus on what
kind of things are going to stress a
system and if we do that it gives us a
much better opportunity to uh to
actually investigate something which we
tend to ignore in our industry which is
how does the system behave when we put
it into production so our industry tends
to focus on the functionality on the use
cases and what we need to be become much
more aware of if we're going to build
systems and deliver them consistently
and well into complex environments is
how does the system behave um how does
the system cope with spikes in load how
does the system cope with changes in the
market around it how does it cope with
social changes and changes in Social
attitude
uh around it and any system that we we
build to be more resilient towards these
kinds of things is going to have a
higher level of quality than those that
we those that we've delivered before so
are you saying that use cases and
functional requirements are not
necessary or are you saying they're not
sufficient I'm saying that that they're
they're not sufficient they're
absolutely not sufficient um so
requirements uh are are a very very
difficult thing in in the complex
environment which I've described outside
of the software we have a some kind of
business function that we're
delivering one way that we deal with uh
with complexity as human beings is to
Outsource it is to make it someone
else's problem and so when I as an
engineer or an architect go to someone
in my business and say tell me your
requirements what I'm actually saying is
I'm Outsourcing the problem of
complexity to you so that when this
project fails it's your fault and it's
actually a form of bullying that we do
to to our partners to our business
stakeholders um youth cases are also
something that uh that that are an issue
for us as I mentioned before we as as
human beings are pattern Seekers and
we'll look for patterns U and we'll base
that on our previous knowledge of the
world something called precedence and
we'll look for patterns and very often
we'll see things that aren't there which
is good because it promotes action in
certain cases but use cases are a
package of things they're a package of
requirements and flows of information
and that are actually quite dangerous
because there's a whole bunch of
assumptions baked into those use cases
and so I tend to not use requirements
definitely not at the start of the
project and I never really use the the
concept of a use case what I tend to do
is to break a system down to the
interactions between the actors in that
system and as we're building Information
Systems then the thing that's
interesting to us is the flow of
information between actors in a system
and so the basic unit of of
decomposition for me in a system is a
flow when a piece of information moves
from one actor in a system to another um
and that means that we take away all of
our bias and all of our preconceived
notions about how a system should work
and it means that we investigate that
fundamental unit in an information
system that actually uh that we know is
going to happen and when we do that that
gives us a base to understand the system
in a much much better way if we're going
to build something that's more resilient
or something that tends towards
antifragility then we need to make sure
that these flows of information can keep
happening or can happen in a slightly
different way and so it's the flows of
information that's important to us as a
modeling concept not the requirement H
and not the use case Okay so let's dive
a little bit more into that you
mentioned something called flows and
information flows specifically in the
context of
stressors and as we dive into that I I I
imagine there's some question in
people's minds about not considering use
cases and not considering requirements
but at some point users are going to
expect their features they're going to
expect that the system does certain
things so how do we get there using this
approach of flows and maybe you can talk
a bit more specifically about how that
works how you identify the flows how you
identify the the stressors that they
address and um how to answer that
question that people might have because
it sounds a bit disconnected I think for
some people to understand how am I ever
going to give my end users what they
want if I'm focusing on what may feel
like a very abstract approach to the
problem yeah and I understand that and
so um eventually we will we will deliver
those features that's that's the that's
the purpose of what we do but uh but
what we're doing now and before we start
to build a system is that we are taking
a step back from functionality and we're
focusing on the systems Behavior so at
the very base of of every project we
ever do there's a business casy case and
there's a business model that we're
trying to accomplish we're trying to
execute on and so everyone has a rough
idea of what the system should actually
do what it should achieve and we tend to
break that down to the features way too
quickly um and the reason for that is
that we want to get started developing
and when we do that then we lose control
of the behavior of the system and and uh
a great deal of my Consulting work
involves actually rescuing projects that
have crashed um in almost all of those
projects I see this rush to deliver
features um but there's nothing wrong
with that in itself but the fact that
the systems behavior is ignored and so
what what what we do in antifragile
systems design is that we start by
focusing on stress we say here we have a
business model that business model is
going to require some for some form of
support in in in terms of
software what kind of things can stress
this business model and so we start with
the obvious one what happens when a
competitor drops their price and so what
what I allow developers to do because
the truth is that system decomposition
is mostly random mostly based on
intuition and very often based on the
last blog article that your lead
developer
read um and so what I do allow people to
decompose the system whatever way they
want okay so Paras wrote about
functional decomposition in 1972 and
we're still doing it in 2019 so it seems
quite instinctive so you won't really
get anywhere if you're constantly
beating people uh up and telling they
have to change the way they do things so
we allow them to decompose the system
whatever way they want and then we say
now we're going to start applying stress
to this system you've designed and so
the first stress is always what happens
when a competitor drops their price in
order to get the engineers to start
thinking that this complicated thing
that you're building is going to live in
a complex environment where you won't be
able to predict everything that's going
to happen and so we change the design a
little bit and we say well you know if a
if a competitor drops their price the
business is going to to do this and so
we're immediately promoting a different
conversation with our business
stakeholders we're asking them we're not
saying tell me your requirements we're
saying tell me what will happen if a
competitor drops their price and then we
adjust the system so that not
necessarily so that the system copes
with that price drop
automatically U although we'll take that
if it's there and it's easy but that we
build the system in such a way that
there is a path to that to the to coping
with what's going to change and the
second stressor which always which
always people very nervous is is lizards
and so I tend to tell people that the
next stressor you're going to deal with
is is giant fire breathing lizards are
going to come up out of the sea they're
going to destroy the city how does the
business cope with this and that seems
ridiculous and it's ridiculous for a
reason because I want people to stop
thinking about probability because when
you start thinking about stress people
tend to go into risk management mode and
risk management is not what we're doing
here we're doing design and risk
management always thinks about
probability and probability isn't even
is is a is a very dangerous subject for
us because it's filled with bias and
none of us actually knows the future
we're completely hopeless at probability
as a species so what we need to do then
is is is is solve this problem how what
are we going to do how are we going to
solve for fire breathing lizards and we
move our design around a little bit and
we put a redundant data center in a
different city that might not get hit by
these fire breathing lizards and maybe
we want to make some things fireproof
and um so we're getting into the actual
Behavior of the system and even though
it might seem like a complete waste of
time if you're a project manager um what
we've actually done is we've shifted the
design around and we can now cope with a
whole bunch of different stressors we
can cope with fire we can cope with
flooding we can cope with war we can
cope with power cuts um we can cope with
social unrest we've solved a whole bunch
of problems and we haven't even had to
think about them and that's the
definition of antifragile is to be able
to respond to stress that we'd never
seen before so by exposing our design to
the imaginary stress of lizards we've
made it stronger towards a whole bunch
of things that we haven't had to think
about yet and so what we do in in what I
call a stressor analysis is that we just
take a spreadsheet and we make a list of
all these things that stress the system
and it's easier to talk about stress
than things that will change because
remember we can't predict what will
change um and the list is too long and
we can never get to the bottom of it and
so I create and it's quite easy to Once
one once you get people engaged in this
it can be quite fun and you come up with
a massive amount of stress these lists
can be quite long um and every time and
what you do is you take one set of your
stressors and you use those to design
the system and you say what changes do
we need to make in our design uh in
order to be able to cope with this kind
of stress and the design then we're
actually pushing the design into the
same kind of process that Real World
antifragile Systems have been a part
party to the reason they become
antifragile is that they're constantly
stressed except we're doing this over
the course of a few days and it's
costing us almost nothing we reserve a
set of stressors then and we we borrow a
trick from machine learning we use the
first set of stressors as our training
set and the second set of stressors as
our testing set to see does the model
actually work and if we've increased the
level of resilience in our system then
what we should see is that we will solve
this this solution will meet the
problems it will survive the problems it
will become stronger when exposed to the
problems that it hasn't been told about
and that's the definition of
antifragility a system that can survive
things that it couldn't possibly have
predicted it couldn't ever have seen and
that gives us um a a a very very simple
tool that does two things one it makes
our systems massively more robust and
more resilient regardless of whether or
not we believe in in in the ability of a
system to become antifragile it makes us
much much more more aware about the
stress that exists in the system and it
makes us closer to the business and all
of those three things are on the
architect's dream ticket and one simple
tool yeah does this for us okay yeah so
you focused a bit again on stressors
there I feel like I'm still a little
fuzzy on flows specifically so maybe you
can speak more to those yeah so so so we
we we're getting to flow so when when
you expose um when you have a system
that's antifragile there's a Norwegian
research called shell yoga researcher
called shelan who wrote a book on
antifragile ICT systems where he
investigated the the concept and said is
it possible for an anti for for an IT
system to be antifragile he came up with
four features of an antifragile system
that and he said yes it is possible
there are antifragile it systems uh
Microsoft's Azure Amazon's AWS great
examples of this and these he came up
with these four properties modularity um
and systems are made up of modules weak
links and that the modules are weakly
linked to each other uh redundancy and
diversity and what what you'll find is
every time you're tweaking your system
every time you expose it to stress and
you change something it will inevitably
one of be one of those four things that
you're changing the level of modularity
of the system the linkage between the
modules the redundancy and
diversity of the components in the
system and so what we want to do then is
to be able to once we've come up with
our stressors once we have a rough shape
of our architecture then we want to say
how do we break this system down into a
number of components and we do that by
investigating um our system as a number
of
flows H and as I said the flow is a
basic unit of of of work in any
information system and so we write down
a list of flows um and then we do some
uh analysis on those and we take a tool
called the design structure Matrix which
is something they use at MIT to decide
which components um Belong Together
inside a single component and which
components need to live their own lives
um outside of this and this uh design
structure Matrix is just a matrix of of
flows against each other and we look for
dependency between flows and out of that
we see which flows need to live together
and we we we introduced some some heris
some rules about these flows we say that
information can go into a flow and it
can leave a flow and and then go into
another flow but information can never
from in inside a flow cross the the flow
boundary and go to another flow it has
to exit the flow and so in that way
we're creating these flows um as modules
in our
system um and then um inside a flow we
say what has to happen inside this flow
the example I always use is a bicycle
shop so we have a a flow called order
bicycle where information flows from me
the consumer to the company saying I
would like a red bicycle with a bell um
and two wheels and that flow then we
look at that we say well what needs to
happen in order for this flow to execute
and it says well we need to check that
this is a registered customer we need to
check that uh that we actually have this
B type of bicycle in stock when we need
to make sure that we have information
payment information and how how we're
going to ship this bicycle to to this
customer all of these things have to H
have to happen for the flow to execute
and so what we want to do then is to
make sure that all of this all of this
code that has to be written is grouped
into components um and those components
will consist of a number of
functions uh and what we then do is that
we run our we go back to our list of
stressors and we produce a stressor flow
and a stressor component Matrix and we
say how many of the flows are impacted
by this particular stressor and inside
the flows how many components are
impacted by a particular stressor and
inside the the component how many
functions are impacted by by a
particular stressor and now we're back
in the world of Paras um where and I
call this Paras counting where we want
to see how many components how many
functions are actually impacted by a
stressor and we look for these patterns
of stress in our components and through
our flows components and the functions
that make up those those components and
anything that has a similar pattern of
reaction to stress gets to live in the
same box and this is how we build up
that modularity and that weak linkage
that's necessary for an antifragile
system and this is this is the the
balance that we have to find because we
cannot put every function in its own
isolated module weekly linked to the
rest of the system because that that
that way lies Madness and so this allows
us to millions millions of microservices
is all interconnected right yes and a
lot of people are trying that and good
luck to them um but so so what we're
actually doing with this this concept of
stressor and flow and playing the two
things off each other is that we're
making guided rational decisions based
on the stress that A System's going to
be exposed to um from the complex
environment that we're forcing it to
live in about where which component
which functions should should be grouped
which components should be grouped and
which flows should be grouped um the
concept that if a stressor acts on the
system what we want to do is is to
prevent contagion um so if a stressor
acts on your system you you want to make
sure that the impact of that stressor
hits as as as small a surface area of
your system as possible and that is how
we get towards um a system having these
four properties of antifragile systems
and we've also tested it with stress so
it's not a theory we've actually seen
that our design responds to the kind of
stress that that that may exist in the
system and we haven't tried to predict
the future and and our stressor list is
incomplete and it's always going to be
incomplete and the mission that we're on
here is to be able to build a system
that responds to stress that it won't
have seen won't be aware of before we
put it into into production and that's
the that's the gist of antifragile
systems design so basically because
you've accommodated many kinds and
categories of stress which which you're
not trying to taxonomize or or or put
into patterns again but you you've
covered enough as you mentioned before
if you can handle the fire breathing
lizard you can by definition handle
other stressors that you have conceived
of and others that you have not even
conceived of the goal is not certainty
the goal is covering your bases with
enough stressors that you have a high
likelihood of survivability or even
Improvement when there's chaos in the
system am I getting that right ex yes
exactly um and so the idea so the
difference between well and talking
about n in Risk Management this is a
real tough point for project managers to
understand I I I don't actually care
about the particular individual stress
or in incidences um because if you just
take individual stress and encapsulate
it um you're not actually doing anything
and you're saying that this system will
work if I have correctly predicted the
future um and and we know from what we
said about complexity earlier that no
matter what happens you have not
correctly predicted the predicted the
future it's not possible in a complex
system to do that and so encapsulation
is not the goal here and what we're
trying to do is to promote the kind of
properties in a system that we see in
systems that are highly resilient and
even Beyond resilient and antifragile so
we don't care about the individual
stress we care about the behavior of the
system connected to
stress uh in its
environment and what this gives us then
is is a
modularization o of our code based on
Flow um and so we have these four really
important Concepts stressor
flows components and
functions and our system is is dependent
on these things now we can start once
you start asking questions about stress
what you'll find is that you start to
get requirements really high quality
requirements because I'm not saying tell
me your requirements which puts a put
puts a business person on the spot and
forces them to answer even if they don't
uh they can't really answer you start to
get a clear picture of non-functional
requirements which is a very difficult
thing and something most Architects
struggle with doing and something most
business people just aren't capable of
doing sure um and that's not their fault
because it's not their job once you once
I ask uh business people what happens
when a competitor drops their price I
start to understand how the business
works I start to understand what's
important I start to understand where
the margins are the requirements start
to become clear with a completely
different level of understanding then
tell me your requirements which will
most of the time just be a description
of a system that does something this
makes it much easier for us to be
Innovative and much easier for us to do
do this thing that everyone's calling
digital transformation because we're in
there with the business trying to
understand what it is that we're
actually trying to achieve and so uh
with the combination of the stressor
analysis and the flow-based
decomposition uh we we get to a design
that has a level of modularity a level
of weak
linkage um that will allow it to it will
hopefully provably be more resilient
than if we had simply sat down and tried
to design something that's resilient and
and use best practices and patterns and
Frameworks and and um you know join the
dots
methodologies
so on what we're actually doing all
these tools are actually are doing is
that they are taking people outside of
their comfort zone outside of this need
to have a plan and executed on forcing
them to partake in real critical
thinking um and also to accept the
reality that the in this system in this
complex system you cannot predict or
control and you have to have other ways
of dealing with that inability to
predict and control so you mentioned a
specific flow before order red bicycle
with a bell yeah how might that actually
be decomposed into modules that maybe
people can sort of start learning how to
think more concretely so you've got the
stressors that you expect well I
shouldn't say that you expect but but
the stressors that are likely to occur
and of course you can't get them all but
you get enough and then you get the
flows that you are going to have through
the system so then what is a modular
decomposition that I might expect to see
to help accommodate the flows that are
going to be going through my system so
the order bicycle is an example of
that's just a single flow through the
system um another flow through the
system um will be
to add a new bicycle to your catalog um
another flow will be
to um set a set a sale price on a
particular bicycle so what we'll say
initially we'll have all of those flows
and there'll be there'll be quite a
number of them and we asked the question
how should these flows live together or
should they or should they exist as
separate Flows In order to prevent
contagion and let's take let's take two
flows as an example order bicycle and
payment or let's say order bicycle and
shipping that's a little bit better so
we have we have one flow that is order
bicycle and information flows from me
the consumer to the company and that and
and that has to execute a whole bunch of
different functions before it can pass
that on to distribution so that they can
do their shipping um and so we have the
second flow which is which is shipping
and so the order comes in um we check
that the bicycles in our inventory and
we have to do that uh we have to check
check that uh payment has gone through
and we have to check that I'm a customer
you have to check that you have my
address that that information was either
in the system already or or came as part
of the message that as part of the flow
that was passed and then we go into the
next flow which is shipping and then we
send a an a piece of paper to an order
to the to the warehouse that says put
this red bicycle with two wheels and a
bell in a box and put this address on it
and send it out
um and so if we were to do all of that
as one single flow imagine we'd been
thinking in terms of use case and the
use case was by
bicycle now we expose it to stress and
here's the here's the stress um we've
decided that apart from just selling
bicycles and we're not also going to
sell tractors which is going to have a
completely different method of
distribution than than bicycles because
it's not something that's going to be
you can't send the tractor through
through the post the same way you can a
bicycle you're going to need different
partners and so um what you have is a
completely different reaction to to this
stressor um
for across these two flows and so what
we're going to say is we need to
separate the shipping
flow from the ordering flow um and
because they they're going to have a
different different response to stress
when we change the stress it when we
bring in the stresser of nording
tractors
uh it will hit the it will hit the
ordering um and it will hit the shipping
in different ways and so they don't
belong inside the same component um and
we do this um it's hard to explain over
a microphone but we do this using uh
using design structure matrices that
allow us to see dependencies between
these different flows and when we see
dependency that asks us to look for a
particular stressor and so I'm jumping
ahead by thinking of what happens if we
change the product that we're sending uh
the second uh type of metrix that we use
is is a is a stressor flow how does
stress impact these different flows and
so if I have bicycles and I have
tractors and I add something else and I
add cars then every time something hits
the every time I add a new product it
changes shipping which has an impact on
every other product that I'm selling so
I have to constantly update that
shipping module then that tells me that
I need to move shipping out into into a
number of separate flows does that make
sense it's not particularly easy to
explain I think so I it it does to me to
my mind it hearkens a bit back to Paras
who you mentioned before and decomposing
in order to his concept of course was
hiding algorithmic complexity hiding uh
various things such as you know how a
function is ordered or or the steps in
it things of this nature but this is
almost sounds like stressor based
decomposition as maybe a summary of what
you're talking about yes it it is it is
stressed um and and there's a level
beyond that which I do in my research
where the decomposition is actually done
using a mathematical tool called a hyper
Network and but we we'll not get into
that today because we won't have time
okay yeah that sounds like maybe another
topic for another
show yeah it's um yeah sort of it's
Advanced geometry and not everyone finds
that entertaining the concept is that we
use stress to guide our our decisions
mind where we are allowed to take
dependencies which is why we use the the
the design structure Matrix and and the
in incidence matrices to see what way do
these components react to stress and so
what we'll do is we'll identify hundreds
of different flows in our system um and
some of those you know we can't
Implement every single one of those
flows as its own as its own separate
system so what we do is we look
for um similar patterns of reaction to
stress and we say these flow those are
going to be hit by the C stressors all
the time there must be some kind of
relationship here let's bring them into
in into a single flow and then we do
this exactly the same thing to decide
which components should be in there and
we do exactly the same thing to decide
which functions should be in the
components and it does come back to par
us a little bit and it sounds like we're
doing uh encapsulation in order to uh
minimize the surface area but what we're
really trying to do is to increase the
resilience of the system um which is how
we measure succcess so encapsulation
remember is not the goal here um even if
encapsulation is a by product of what
we're doing what we're trying to do is
to increase the ability of the system to
respond to unknown stress so are there
some
particular techniques that people can
use to help them discover what the
stressors might be to their system I I
guess I appreciate the the silliness of
getting people out of their maybe um
rigid mindset by using dragon dragon and
and things of that nature but when it
comes down to it you know for example I
can imagine business people hearing this
conversation and saying this sounds like
a lot of upfront design it sounds like
it's expensive it's going to take a long
time and we just want to start writing
software and shipping features so how do
you respond to that and then uh are
there some techniques that can help you
shorten the time frames to identifying
your your flows and your stressors in
your system yeah so I I think if you go
and speak to senior Architects um who
are designing successfully designing
delivering systems they're doing this
kind of thing um it it's just very very
difficult for them to
articulate um so it doesn't really take
that much time a stressor analysis um
does not take does not take a great deal
of time but one of the things that we
always talk about is is they're going is
this going to increase the cost and
absolutely if you come up with a
solution a mitigation to every single
stressor that you see um you're going to
it's going to seem like you're that
you're building the system to cope with
things that are never going to happen
and people will ask well is that a just
is there a Justified return on that kind
of on that kind of thing um and here we
go back to talb who talks about convex
strategies um for building systems that
are antifragile and what what happens is
that we look at everything we can do at
the design stage that costs very very
little money in order to uh make make
it capable um of coping with of coping
with that stress and that might mean
just moving a few functions from one
component to another in order to prevent
contagion across different flows and to
lower the cost of actually making a
change if we need to make that change in
the future a lot of that stuff doesn't
cost any money for those mitigations
that do cost money there's a the third
step after your stressors after your
flow-based
analysis um the Third step in the in the
antifragile systems design process is
the trade-off step um and when you have
solutions that are concave and that
you're going to have to spend a lot of
money on something that has a very small
risk then you don't automatically build
that into your system you lift that up
um to a wider group of stakeholders in
the project and say should we do this or
should we not and in the antifragile
systems design we use something um in
the simplest case something called atam
the architecture trade-off and Analysis
method as a way of guiding that
conversation and then we're getting into
the real world of risk management that
our project managers are used to now we
actually want to talk about should we
manage this risk or not um should we
invest in mitigating this risk or not
whereas previously what we've been doing
is using the concept of stress to push
our design in a particular direction I
see so if you push your design to the
limits to accommodate all stressors you
can come up with this astronomically
expensive system that's meant to
accommodate every possible stressor but
now you bring that to the actual
business stakeholders and you begin to
discuss sort of bringing this down to
reality you know we've we've considered
a system that's expansive and can cover
all all of these possible bases but
that's obviously prohibitively expensive
and also not every stressor has the same
risk level so now we're going to kind of
bring that down to reality is that is am
I hearing you right yes so all all the
stressor all the mitigations for
stressors that you've seen that are
actually going to cost a substantial sum
of money you bring those all the ones
that don't cost any money or can be
mitigated by simple design changes you
implement those regardless of the
propability because we're we're not
interested in mitigating individual
stressors we want to lift the ability of
the system to cope with
stress and the the result of that work
even if the business shuts down every
single one of your con of your con
strategies which cost a lot of money for
to mitigate small risks the system
should still be um definitively more
more resilient than it was when we
started the design process which brings
us then to the final step in the
antifragile systems design process which
is the failure mode effects analysis and
in that then now we've we've broken down
our system into a number of flows we've
decided which components are going to
exist in those flows and which functions
should be in there we then take it Flow
by flow and we go to our spreadsheet
where we have our stressor analysis we
open a second Tab and we work through
that Tab and we write down the failure
modes of every component inside each of
these flows and now we're looking at the
internal stress in a system not the
external stress so we're saying here we
have a que what are the failure modes of
that que and we can say that this queue
can slow down it can crash the server
that it's on can crash it can receive
poison
messages and what we'll start to see as
we move through that list is that we'll
mitigate each one of these failure modes
and we'll we'll try to make the system
as self-healing as possible so that um
we detect and fix errors as um
automatically if possible but as fast as
we possibly can with as little expense
as we possibly can and as we move down
through both of these lists the stressor
analysis and the failure mode analysis
what you'll start to realize is as you
move down through these lists it becomes
incredibly difficult to stress the
system it becomes incredibly difficult
to find examples of internal or external
stress that actually damage your system
and that's how you know you're on the
right path path because you've built
something that's responding to stress
that you have stress both internal and
external that you haven't seen before
and this leads to something called
exaptation and exaptation is where two
functions of a system two mitigations
that we put in place um unrelated can
actually combine to cope with the with
problems that they never seen that that
the system had never seen before the
example often given is one of dinosaurs
and so back in time there were these
little tiny dinosaurs who had a huge
stresser and that was bigger dinosaurs
kept eating them um and so the the
dinosaurs who had evolved um small
cloths they survived better because they
they they were able to climb trees and
get away from the big dinosaurs uh that
were eating them but they had they they
they developed a new problem them a new
form of stress they were exposed to
which was the cold when they were up in
the trees and so the cold was causing
them to to die and the the ones that had
developed feathers they survived the
cold because they had feathers um and
then a third form of stress came along
and that was the wind and sometimes the
wind would blow and knock them out of
the trees and one day one of the little
guys with feathers blew out of the tree
stuck out his arms and and got some
uplift and that's how we got birds not
by Design but through mitigating
different forms of stress and developing
different functions to cope with
different types of stress and they
eventually were able to combine Bine
those things in a way that allows us to
cope with stress that we hadn't thought
of or hadn't designed and so what we're
what we're attempted to do here is to
replace this uneasiness in Architects
and say it's okay not to have a plan
it's okay not to be in control it's okay
not to know everything and it's okay
that you're the reason that you
succeeded was based on
intuition um and and not on on following
a plan or a process and this idea of
exaptive system design is is what we're
trying to get to with anti with
antifragile systems design it's not
something you can ever guarantee but it
um in all the projects that I have to go
into and rescue and and do reviews on if
you were to carry out if you were to
take the four things I've mentioned the
stressor analysis the flow Bas
decomposition the architecture tradeoff
and the failure mode effects analysis if
you take one of those techniques and
apply it to any project you'll get a
massive lifting quality if you take all
four together you'll get an enormous
lifting quality around the behavior of
the system system um and also the
capacity to uh to actually meet problems
that possibly the capacity to meet
problems that you'd never seen before
there are no guarantees in this but when
you're working with complex systems then
there there are no guarantees full stop
there's no way to do this and be right
all the time well if people want to get
started with learning more about
antifragile architecture or learning
about how get they can apply some of
these techniques in their own uh
environments where should they get
started uh well there there is some um
there are some articles published uh I
I've been publishing a series of
Articles through cutter uh business
technology Journal o over the last year
I guess if you go and and add me on
LinkedIn um you'll see that list of
articles there under my Publications um
there are also courses that we hold
regularly there's a a two-day course on
antifragile business architecture a
4-day course on uh antifragile Solutions
architecture there's also an
introductory course um that introduces
all of the stuff you need to know in
order to be able to do stressor analysis
properly such as what is a business
what's a business model what's a what is
organizational culture how do I
understand all of these things that an
architecture an architect needs to
understand in order to be able to
succeed and how much of that is also
relevant for business people to be
learning and becoming more aware of it's
absolutely relevant um especially um if
you look at the impact so one of the
things I find is that if you're actually
practicing this in the real world as an
architect you you start to impact the
business model and the operating model
because when you ask about particular
types of stress it might be that
business people haven't thought about
these things and they'll need to make
changes in the operating model or small
changes in the business model in order
to be able to uh to mitigate certain
kinds of stress um and so what I find is
that from my public seminars I've had a
a demand from business people business
analysts business Architects who've
wanted to to learn this but not go in
deep into the to the flow Bas
decomposition uh and and so that's why
we've had to create the shorter course
okay so how can people find out more
about what you're up to you I think you
mentioned LinkedIn before there any
other places they can get more
information about about you and your
company um I think LinkedIn is is
probably the best place at the minute
it's where I'm most active uh my
literature review from my PhD I'm doing
that out live so I'm constantly posting
what I'm reading and where this stuff is
coming from and and so the the LinkedIn
page is is
definitely uh the best place to see what
I'm doing um what's on my mind on a
particular day um for courses um in
Sweden I work with the Swedish computer
Society um and so check in their website
which is uh data fors competence PS for
anyone listening in Sweden
um and we'll post a link to that in the
show Notes too for us English speakers
who don't know what you just
said yeah um uh and there you'll see the
schedule for the courses um but the
LinkedIn feed is where I'm where I'm
most active I I have a Twitter Rec as
well which is technology
chulip it's uh it's there's not as much
happening there as there is on LinkedIn
okay great and then you also have your
company website black top. correct yes I
do okay great Barry thank you very much
for this discussion about antifragile
architecture yep thanks Jeff thanks for
having me on this is Jeff dittle for
software engineering radio thanks for
listening thanks for listening to SC
radio an educational program brought to
you by It software magazine for more
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at se-
radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter
or through our slack Channel at seo.
slack.com you can also email us at
team-
radio.net this and all other episodes of
SE radio is licensed under creative
commment license
2.5 thanks for